Chinese bank
loans just
showed a
record decline.
Record reduction.
Just when you think the
situation in China
can't get any worse,
they find a
way to make it worse.
And that's not all.
The Chinese government
has prepared a surprise,
especially for
wealthy people, which
makes us ask:
why now?  This is
largely a
rhetorical question,
but they have taken up
taxes, which could be a
prelude to bigger
events and
larger-scale
repression, because,
as I said,
the situation in China is getting worse and worse
.  So,
we got the
macroeconomic data
that confirmed everything,
but the real story
here is the banks and
Beijing.  Banks and Beijing,
tightening the nuts.
Record reduction in
overall
social
financing and
new yuan
loans in China.
So, these are the credit
flows for July.  Yes,
July is a seasonal
low point in the
calendar, which
really only
exposes how
dire the situation is for
Chinese banks.  And
Chinese banks, as
we know, have been
retreating for
several years now, and if
you haven't seen it yet,
wait until I
show you the next
chart, because it
really illustrates what
we're talking about here
.  Chinese
banks are the backbone of the
Chinese economy
.  This is precisely the mechanism through which
China responded to the
consequences of the 2008 crisis
.  Without the
banking sector,
they wouldn't have a
real estate bubble.  But
now that this
bubble has popped,
they have not
corrected the economic
situation—the "silent
depression," which I
will talk about at the end of
this video.  A silent
depression, a housing bubble
—they don't have the
economy to
support this
bubble, so the banks
piled up and
piled up bad
loans, not just from
real estate, but also from
local government
projects and
obligations.  This is also
involved,
especially the tax
scheme.  And all this only
shows that
there is a
huge bubble in China, the largest
in human history
, which
belongs to and is the fault of the
Chinese
banking sector
.  And what is happening in the
Chinese
banking sector
?  Well, there are a bunch of
hidden credits there.
You can't have
such a massive
collapse without these
loans and bad
debts
piling up somewhere.  So
we know what's
happening in the
Chinese
banking sector
, even if we
don't have direct data to
show it.  We
have all the supporting data
around this.  We
don't have direct
information about
how bad the
situation is, but
in many ways we don't
need it.  It would be
nice, but it is not
necessary, because we
can understand what is
really
happening in China
by observing the
behavior of the
banking sector there
.  Discard government
spending, don't take it
into account.  What matters is not what
is said in
China, but what
Chinese banks actually do.  And that's
not what
central banks do—
never central,
it's commercial
banks, not central.    What
matters is what the
banking sector does.  And
, as you can see,
there is a
record reduction.
Even if this is a
seasonal low in the
lending calendar, it is
quite consistent
with the trend.
Let's look at the
following graph, as
I said.  These are new
credit flows from
Chinese banks in
yuan in the first seven
months of each year.
So, we compare
comparable indicators
.  And you see 2024,
which we've been talking about
on this channel since the
very beginning,
the situation is getting worse and worse
.  There
was a small
revival in early 2025 that everyone
attributed to the “bazooka” of
September 2024, but
it was a
short-term
coincidence, not a true
reversal.  And the situation
in 2026, which this
graph shows very
clearly, has become even
worse, which
is consistent with the
economic recession,
or more precisely, the
accelerated recession,
which we have been
talking about again on
this channel since
last summer.
Macroeconomic data
confirms this, as do
banking
sector data.  And all of this is
consistent with
interest
rates.  China is the
best example, a
current example of the
fallacy of
interest rates
that Milton Friedman spoke about
.  People
keep saying that
low interest
rates are a stimulus,
even though that's not the case at all.
Low rates are a
reflection of
economic weakness,
and in this case,
therefore higher risk, as
well as the weakness of the
Chinese
banking sector
.  So, interest
rates fall
in line with the actions
of banks.  Remember
2018-2019, the "minefield
" as we call it here
, from the end of
2018.  At that time,
there was a
slowdown
in lending as
Chinese banks
abandoned
risky
behavior and bought
huge amounts of
safe government
bonds.  So
government
bond yields are falling,
signaling the
weakness of the economy
and the financial
system, which is
recognized in this
case because China is
very dependent on the
banking sector
, and these banks
are doing something.  You see it in the
bond market, in the
banking
statistics, in the
real economy, you
see it everywhere except in
mainstream economic
theory, and therefore in the
mainstream media,
which continues
to insist that lower
rates are a stimulus,
even though China is the
perfect
real-world experiment, which
once again confirms the
fallacy about
interest rates:
lower rates are a
sign of weakness.
Again, the last
few years,
look,
look what we
have here.  A big
drop in
Chinese government
bond yields, especially
long-term ones, but also
short-term ones
.  But the big
drop in
long-term
government bond yields is
consistent with
Chinese banks
retreating.  So,
Chinese bank balance sheets are
significantly
de-risking, I
mean, just
look at this
chart, it's way off
trend and it's getting
worse.  They
reduce risks.  They
stop
lending to anything
that even slightly smacks of
risk, not only in the
household sector, but also
in the corporate
sector.  They
reduce risks.  And
by reducing risks, they
buy security.  This is a
depression economy.
This should be very
familiar, at least to
people who are honest and
have been paying attention, to our
experience here in the
Western world,
post-2008.  Yes,
China hasn't had a
2008-style crash, but
they've been trying to
work to
avoid something like that
for
about a decade.
And during this
decade, it was a kind of
2008, but
stretched and
extended over a
ten-year period, rather than
compressed into a couple of
years like we saw
here in the Western
world.  So
lower interest
rates,
falling sharply,
consistent with
Chinese banks
reducing risk and a
depressed economy,
tells you everything you
need to know about
Chinese banks,
as well as interest
rates.  The next
time you hear
someone say, in China
or abroad, that
lower interest
rates are a stimulus,
remember this graph,
as well as the graphs I'll
show you next.  And what
has happened in the last
few years, as
Chinese banks
retreat,
the economy
deteriorates,
accelerating the decline,
what we hear from
Western media,
economists,
central bankers
?  Stimulus.  And so we
go through this
cycle in China, these
mini-cycles in China.
Minicycles are a topic
we keep
coming back to here at
Eurodollar University in the
2020s.  But the mini-cycle in
China was about
"oh no,
the economy isn't working the way
we thought."  Here's some more
incentive for you
.  Oh no, the economy does
n't work the way we
thought.  Here's some more
incentive for you.  Oh no,
the economy doesn't work the way
we thought.  Here's some more
incentive for you
.  And every time
stimulus fails to
stimulate,
economists
get excited about
expecting even
more
stimulus from the
Chinese government,
which does
absolutely nothing.
Instead, we see
lower interest
rates, banks
continue to wind down
operations, and
China is
accelerating into
recession.  This is the main
theme, whether general
or specific.
The general theme is
the fallacy of
interest rates
and the economics of
depression, and the specific
theme of this video is
why now, why is
the situation in China
accelerating even
more.  So, again
, to emphasize
: lower interest
rates are consistent
with lower growth in
bank
lending.  So
the volume of outstanding
yuan loans in
China, that is, virtually
all local
currency loans, which make up the
vast majority of
lending in
Chinese banks,
continues to hit
record lows.  And
look, the growth rate is
accelerating
downward just as
Chinese bond yields
began to
fall sharply.  Remember
2024, when the People's
Bank of China
specifically
warned Chinese
banks: "Don't buy
government bonds,
because when we
introduce stimulus,
not only will you
get a flood of
government bonds
in the market, but it will also
work, so you won't
want to buy
safety."  And the Chinese
banks responded: "You
guys have no idea what you're
talking about."  And they
kept
buying government
bonds, and here we are
2 years later
, and the banks
turned out to be absolutely
right.
Risk reduction, lower rates
, and NBK incentives have not
worked.  The state
proposal is
another parallel to
the situation in the
United States.
The state proposal
does not change the situation.
What changes it is the
fundamentals of
depression economics.  Low
growth, low
inflation
expectations, which are
no longer just
expectations, they are
becoming a reality in
the economy.  So, once again
, low rates are not
incentives.  They
indicate that a
depressed economy is occurring.
There is some credit growth in the Chinese economy.  We look at
aggregate financing of the
real
economy, which is a
broad measure of
credit creation and movement.  In this
case, it is more of a
flow than a residue.
So, a broad
measure of credit
flow into the Chinese
economy, and you
see it
growing over the
last few
years, but we just
figured out that it
can't be from
Chinese banks,
so it's not
bank
lending.
Instead, it's
government bonds,
which further proves
my point about stimulus
.  Government actions, public
borrowing and
spending at the
fiscal level, as well as
at the
central bank level,
are primarily
a reaction to weakness,
not a correction
or solution to it.  And this is
very clearly visible
if you look at
the behavior of Chinese
government bonds.
Going back, in essence
, to the third
quarter of 2018, this
is the same time bomb
.  We
at Eurodollar University
talk
about this mine all the time.
At least I've been saying
this in various
forms for almost a
decade,
starting in the third
quarter of 2018.
Very serious changes.
But the fact that everything
turned out this way is
no coincidence.  This is
beyond the scope of
this video.  The
timing in 2018 was no
coincidence, but since
then, the
weaker
China's economy has become, the
more the government
has tried to
do something.  And the more
the government intervenes, the
less it produces
results, which
means we
go through the same
mini-cycle.  Stimuli
fail, the government
does more,
stimulus fails again
, the government
ramps up
efforts again, and soon
government bonds are
piling up everywhere they
can.  And these
numbers are simply
staggering.
In fact, since 2024,
and even earlier, but
starting with the "bazooka" of
2024, the Chinese
government has borrowed a
huge, simply
incredible amount, and bond
rates have
still
fallen.
Growth fundamentals and
inflation
expectations weigh
much more than
government supply.
In fact, in
this depressed
economy,
only expectations about
growth and
inflation matter.  So when
banks back down,
saying they don't want to take
the risk, and
the government steps in because
it's the only player on the
field, it's the
banks that matter, not the incentives.  And
you can see
exactly what I'm talking about.
This is an inverse
correlation, although it should
be direct.  The issuance of
government bonds
must increase, and therefore
economic growth must also increase
.  That's what everyone says.  Here is the
data.  Here is the
evidence.
Government bond issuance has
skyrocketed, and what
happened to
economic
growth in China?
It fell.  This is exactly what
I'm telling you.
Low rates are not
incentives.  Government
bonds are not
incentives.  Low
rates are, first and
foremost, a market forecast
for growth and
inflation.  Low
rates from a
policy perspective mean
that central banks
are responding to what the
market has already
signaled.
Central banks
follow the market, taking into
account, you know,
different time lags.
And government actions, spending,
and borrowing—are
also a reaction to
weakness, not an
answer or a
fix
.  So, low rates
are not an incentive, and you
can see that in the
following chart.
Again, lower
10-year
bond yields in China
correspond to a decline in
economic
growth rates.  And it's
not just about "zero
tolerance" for COVID or
lockdowns.  Overall, the
Chinese system has
been slowing down and
slowing down since the
third quarter of
2018, actually since the
second quarter of
2018, but it's more clearly
visible since the third
quarter of 2018.    A
mine appears, and the
world changes.  And this
mine came about because of the
last graph that
I'm going to show you in this
video.  So, once again:
low rates are not an
incentive.  Chinese
banks are reducing
risks.  This has
economic consequences.
This is the main idea of
this issue.  It's
not just that
banks are pulling back
from the
real estate sector and
financing
developers.  There are
real economic
consequences for the entire
Chinese economy,
including what you
see here in GDP,
especially real
GDP, which shows that the
real economy
is being held back by a
lack of risk-taking
among Chinese
banks and businesses.  But
Chinese banks are
backing down,
Chinese
borrowers don't
want to borrow,
Chinese lenders
don't want to lend, and the
real economy is
slowing more and
more,
consistent with
low interest
rates and a
depressed
economy.  This is a
consistent story, and
I think
it
only causes
confusion and
misunderstanding for most people, because you
are taught that low
interest rates are a stimulus,
even though all historical
experience suggests
otherwise, which is what
Friedman was saying in
1967.  This contradicts all
historical
experience.  This
contradicts what
academic economists say.  This
Wall Street says.
Reality,
empirical reality
, is the exact
opposite of what
you hear on
social media
or on television.
Low interest rates,
depressed economy
, demand for security.  And
here we see
banks taking
risks off the table by
cutting
lending and
buying government
bonds.  And the real
economy seems to be
somewhere in the middle.  And the
worse
the economy gets, the more
it convinces
Chinese banks that
they should cut back on
lending, which
means buying
more government
bonds.  The more
government bonds the central government
issues, the more
banks buy them, the
worse the
economy gets, the deeper
they fall into this
trap.  This is called the
zero-
lower-bound trap, but
it's really just
macroeconomics,
basic economics, which of
course "real
" economists with
PhDs don't really
understand.
Let's talk about these
big changes in
public policy
recently.  The government
has announced a crackdown
on
tax evasion among the
ultra-rich.  This
came as
a surprise to some, although the
legal basis for
this has existed in China for
a long time.  This is not a
new law that
has been passed, and it is not a
new, how would you
say, new
measure introduced by
the government.  In fact, this is a
long-standing policy that
Chinese
officials have
simply turned a blind
eye to until recently.  Now they
say, okay, we're
starting to
enforce the law, which
means you
have to pay
taxes on the
capital gains that you've
been hiding offshore,
and we know where it all
lies.  They're giving
everyone 120 days, or 60
days, I think, until
October—however many
days it turns out to be, which is
a couple of months—to
file their tax
returns and
pay their taxes before
additional
penalties are assessed, which
involve more
severe penalties
and threats than
just a higher
tax bill.
So, they are very
serious
about returning
some of these taxes,
and the question arises:
why now?  As I
said, this law has
been in effect all this time.
It was not being implemented,
but suddenly the Chinese
authorities decided that it
needed to be
implemented.  As I
mentioned in the introduction to
this video, we already
know the answer.  This is a
rhetorical question.
The situation in China
is deteriorating quite
significantly, and in many
cases quite
rapidly.  So the idea behind
this measure is to
raise
more funds for
local
governments, as they
find themselves caught in the
crossfire
between the
de-risking process in the
Chinese
banking sector
that I just
talked about and the
macroeconomics that is
suffering from the
effects of the
real estate market crash and the
credit crunch.  This
put the local
government in a rather
pitiful state.
In fact, many
reports indicate
that local
authorities are not
paying
suppliers, not
paying some
employees, and not
providing basic services.
That's the situation, and
you also have to
remember that with all the
debt that
local
governments have issued—both
directly and
through financial
instruments—this is
risky debt
that even
banks avoid.  So, one of the
purposes of this
tax pressure
is, in fact, to send
a signal, but the other
important part,
the financial part, is that
we need
more tax
revenues for
local
governments to strengthen
their finances, and if
we get those funds
, hopefully
some of this debt
can be sold at
reasonable prices.  And
perhaps these local
governments that
were effectively
cut off from the
credit markets
will be able to come back
and
access them again.  So in
a lot of ways, this is
done to
strengthen their
budgets to
help pay
some of these bills.
What do they call it here
?  The "
Raising Hands" campaign.  There
are several different
meanings here.  But, actually, to
strengthen the finances of
local governments so that
they can start
paying their
bills, and also,
perhaps, start
entering the
bond market.  And again
, the question is "why
now?"  arises because
the situation in the
real economy
has worsened.  The fact that
the situation is
worsening is
apparently recognized by
China's banking sector, which
is experiencing a
record contraction
and fall in
bank
lending.  Therefore,
a record deterioration
in the real economy
threatens local
authorities.
The situation threatens
to become even worse than
it already is for these
local
governments.  So
the central government in
Beijing seems to be saying: we
need to
do something before it
gets much
worse.  As I always
say here, the more
they feel they have to
do something, the
worse the
situation becomes, you know.  And this is a
rather serious
step that may
lead to
further measures in
the future, up to the
introduction of
capital controls, but this is already a
bit of a leap
forward.  The
focus now is on
taxes and strengthening
local
government finances, not
necessarily on cracking down on
money moving out of
China, which we've
seen before, but it's a
pretty drastic move.
And to reinforce the
macroeconomic side of
this issue:
the effects of the credit
cycle
are indeed shifting towards
recession.  You look
at some of the latest
macroeconomic data
, we got the
PMI indices earlier this
month and throughout the
year.  Earlier
this month, the
manufacturing PMI
unexpectedly
faltered, which is
important but also a
surprise.
This is important because the
manufacturing sector
is the part of China
that has performed
quite well so far.
The Chinese are still
experiencing an
export boom, but
also a domestic
economic downturn.
So, we have an
export boom and a
domestic recession, and
if the domestic recession
turns out to be worse than the
export boom, the
export
boom itself will be in
danger because the
Europeans are
following Donald
Trump into a
trade war.  Er
, then you get
both sides at the
same time.  So the
manufacturing sector
is what is still
holding the Chinese
economy on a very
thin thread in the
face of really
significant
headwinds, which
is one of the reasons
why Chinese banks are
reducing risk in
this way and
accelerating this
process, because it's
not just about where
China is today, but
where
Chinese banks think it's
going tomorrow, which,
by the way, the Chinese government seems to see,
hence the tax
crackdown.  So, there
are more and more
consistent signs,
including
macroeconomic confirmation, that
the situation is indeed
getting worse.  And it has been getting
significantly worse
since last summer, as
we have been pointing out ever since
.  The
non-manufacturing PMI
for July
appears to have been
exactly 49, one of the
lowest readings on
record.  You haven't
seen anything
like this since the
lockdowns in late
2022.  If
you look at it
historically or before we
get to what
I said
earlier, the
rate change, you can see a
clear deterioration and
acceleration of the recession
starting last
summer, which we've
been pointing to in all the
macroeconomic
data that
banks in
China are responding to.  So, a significant
acceleration into the
downturn, but one of the
lowest rates
on record, which I
think pretty accurately
reflects what
the banks and the
central government are seeing, and
so it's consistent
with the low
interest rates
and the bullish
steepness of the curve,
which we continue to
see in the
Chinese government
bond market.  So when
you have a central
bank that doesn't
intervene because there's
no inflation
, there's a complete,
recognizable, and
obvious "bullish"
inversion of the
Chinese bond curve,
or any other
curve where there's no
central bank intervention.  And
macroeconomic data
continues to
confirm everything
we just
talked about.
Macroeconomics not
only gets caught up in this
mess, but also acts as
part of a
self-reinforcing feedback mechanism,
leading to the next
stage.  And stimulation
is simply a reaction
to everything that continues
to happen.  This did not
improve the situation
despite years of
constant
encouragement from
the Chinese.  In many
ways, the Chinese just
do what the
textbooks tell them to do, and in
many ways, they
don't really have
much choice.  From the
government's perspective, it really
comes down to
this nonsense about
saving
jobs.  They cannot
create a recovery
.  This may not
stop the economic
downturn completely, but it may
be able to
mitigate the
negative consequences somewhat
so that it does not
turn into a
disorderly collapse of the
economy and
financial system.
Therefore, perhaps the
Chinese
stimulus is having a
positive effect,
saving some
jobs.  I mean, that's what
we've been hearing about
stimulus
throughout the Western
world for the last 20 years
.  At least from those
who are honest about it
, which is almost nobody, but
maybe they are
saving jobs,
and that is really the
view: we can't
stop the recession, but we
can maybe
make it
at least manageable,
which is where I
got the term "
managed decline" many years ago.
But the bottom line for those who
are encountering this for the first time:
stimulation does not
stimulate.  In many
ways, that's not even the
goal.  This will not change
China's economic fortunes or
its financial
situation.  And that
led to
tax crackdowns
to try to
help on the
fiscal side.
So the graph that I
showed at the end of
this video explains a lot
about where
China is right now.  We have
industrial
production, as I
said, which is artificially
supported, in
many ways artificially, by the
export sector
and the export boom.
And you can see
the difference here when you
overlay that on
retail sales.
If we go back to the
early years of the
late
Eurodollar period, that is, the
1990s and early 2000s
, we can see how the
export boom
contributed to domestic
economic
growth.  So you
have exports that are
booming thanks to
globalization, the
heyday of the Eurodollar,
this is its most
mature period.
Industrial
production drives the
growth of
China's domestic economy
because not only do you
have the investments that
need to be made so that
China can
serve the rest of the
world.  It also
increases incomes and
jobs.  And so you have
this very good
symbiosis between an
export boom and
domestic
economic
growth,
financed
entirely by Chinese
banks, which are also
expanding rapidly
both domestically
and with
dollars coming in
through various foreign
channels.  But what
ultimately happens
after 2008?  Well, the
global economy is still
not
recovering.  And so
China suffers to some extent
on the
industrial side,
because when you
set out to be the "
factory of the world," and
suddenly the world doesn't want
much from factories,
you have
depressed
industrial circumstances
, which also
depresses
investment.  You know,
the term "ghost town
" is coming up for the first time
because some of these
construction projects
turned out to be not so much
ghost towns or the
result of
overbuilding, but rather an
unexpected
slowdown, which caused the
ghost towns to
pile up
instead of being
populated as
planned.  So, the
industrial economy
is suffering from a silent
depression, and the domestic
economy
is also starting to decline,
which is putting pressure on the
real estate sector, which should have
bridged this
gap, but in fact has
not.  So
we have Chinese
banks that massively
increased
lending to an
economy that
continued to disappear
both externally and
internally.  So,
you can understand
where this
situation came from even before
we got to
2020, before we
got to 2018.  In
2018, Xi Jinping
finally realized that
China had chosen
this course, and then a
managed decline began to manifest itself;  that's
one of the reasons why we
see that huge
tipping point, that
very clear
tipping point with the time mine at
the end of 2018.
But for our purposes
here, in 2026, we can
see that
retail sales have
fallen very sharply over the last couple of years.  These are
reduced risks,
lack of
credit growth,
increased restrictions on
credit and
cash flows,
and the fact that the
Chinese economy
is experiencing its own
significant difficulties.
Although the export boom
does exist as a
last resort
to support the economy.
Not stimulation, but an
export boom.
So China is overly
dependent on an
export boom
just to
keep
things going
until things
get even worse, which
puts an
entire
economy of this
size, complexity,
and with so many
imbalances in a precarious position.  It's
understandable from a
banker's perspective why you
might not want to
take on a lot of
risk.  You may
want to shift
some of your
loan portfolio
into safe government
bonds, regardless
of
central government
or central
bank policies.  You look at
it and say, "I
need to reduce my
risks."  "Give me
safety."  "Give me
government bonds."
Government
bond yields are falling.
The economics of depression.    It
all fits
together perfectly.
When you step outside of
mainstream
capital-E economics into simple,
basic, intuitive
lower-e economics, the world
becomes completely
understandable, including what the
Chinese and Chinese
banks are doing.  So, in July,
Chinese banks
recorded
a reduction in
lending.
Meanwhile, the Chinese
government is beginning to take
tough measures,
using
existing laws, which
indicates that
the authorities understand the
worsening situation.
So the more
they think they have to
do,
the worse things actually are, you
know
.  And we already
know that things are getting worse,
because Chinese bankers
understand this and act
accordingly.  So we
should be watching
developments in China closely,
especially what the
government crackdowns and
purges will lead to, how
fast the downturn might be
, and whether the
main risk lies in the
unfolding credit
crunch that
underlies everything
related to the
post-2008 housing bubble
.
This has been building up in
China for twenty years, and now we are
starting to see the
negative consequences
really coming to the
surface.  So we
have to watch
China, and then there's the
energy shock on
top of everything
else—because why not
?  We are missing one more
thing.  So thank you very much for
joining
me.
See you all soon
.